okay this is lecture five in linear
algebra and uh it will complete this
chapter of the
book so the last section of this chapter
is
2.7 that talks about
permutations which finished the previous
lecture and transposes which also came
in the previous lecture there's a little
more to do with those guys permutations
and
transposes but then the heart of the
lecture will
be the beginning of what you could say
is the beginning of linear
algebra the beginning of real linear
algebra which
is seeing a bigger picture with Vector
spaces not just vectors but spaces of
vectors and subspaces of those spaces so
we're a little ahead of the
syllabus which is good because we're
coming to the place where uh there's a
lot to
do okay so to begin with
permutations can I just uh
so so so these permutations
those are matrices p and they
execute row
exchanges
and we may need them we may have a
perfectly good Matrix a perfect Matrix a
that's invertible that we can solve ax
equal
B but to do it I've
got to allow myself that extra freedom
that if a zero shows up in the pivot
position I move it away I get a nonzero
I get a proper pivot there by exchanging
from a row
below and you've seen that already and I
just want to collect the ideas together
and in in principle I could even have to
do that two times or more
times so I have to allow to complete the
the the the the the possibility that I
take my Matrix a I start elimination I
find out that I need row exchanges and I
do it and continue and I finish okay
then all I want to do is say and I won't
make a big project out of
this what happens to a equal
Lu so a equal
luu Lu this this was a matrix L with
ones on the diagonal and zeros above and
multipliers below and this will U we
know with zeros down
here that's only possible that that
description of elimination assumes that
we don't have a p that we don't have any
row exchanges and now I just want to say
okay how do I count for row exchanges
because that
doesn't the p in this factorization is
the identity Matrix the rows were in a
good order we left them
there maybe I'll just add a little
moment of reality too
about how matlb actually does
elimination mat lab not only checks
whether that pivot is not zero as as as
every human would do it checks for is
that pivot big enough because it doesn't
like very very small pivots pivots close
to zero are numerically bad so actually
if we ask matlb to solve a system it
will do some elimination some some row
exchanges which we don't think are
necessary algebra doesn't say they're
necessary but uh accuracy numerical
accuracy says they are
well we're doing algebra
so here we will say well what would what
do row exchanges do but we won't do them
unless we have to but we may have
to and
then the result
is it's hiding here it's the main
fact this is the description of
elimination with row exchanges so a
equal luu
becomes paal
Lu this so This p is the Matrix that
does the row exchanges and actually it
does
them yeah it it it gets the rows into
the right order into the good order
where pivots will not where zeros won't
appear in the pivot position where L and
U will come out right as as up here so
that's the that's the
point actually I don't want to labor
that
point that a permutation
Matrix and you remember you remember
what those were can I just I'll remind
you from last time of what the main
points about permutation matrices
were
and and then just leave this
factorization
as the general case this is this becomes
this is for
any
invertible
a we get this for almost everyone we
don't need a p but there's that handful
that do need row exchanges and if we do
need them there they are okay finally
just to remember what P was
so
permutations p
is the the
identity
Matrix
with reordered
rows
so well I include in reordering the
possibility that you just leave them the
same so the identity Matrix is is okay
that's like the basic your basic
permutation Matrix well
your your do nothing permutation Matrix
is the identity and then there are the
ones that exchange two rows and then the
ones that exchange three rows and then
the ones that exchange
four well it gets a
little the the it gets more interesting
algebraically if you've got four rows
you you might exchange them all in one
big cycle 1: 2 2: 3 3: 4 4: 1 or you
might have exchange one and two and
three and four lots of possibilities
there in fact how many
possibilities the answer was n
factorial this is n * n -1 * N - 2 * 3 *
2 * 1 that's the number of of this
counts
the reorderings the possible
reorderings so it
counts all the N byn
permutations and all those matrices have
these have this nice property that
they're all
invertible because we can bring those
rows back into the normal
order and the Matrix that does that is
just p is just the same as the
transpose you might take a permutation
Matrix multiply by its transpose and
you'll see how that the
ones hit the ones and give the ones in
the identity Matrix so this is a
we'll be highly interested in matrices
that have nice properties and one
property that maybe I could rewrite that
as P transpose p is the
identity that tells me in in other words
that that this is the inverse of
that okay we we'll be interested in
matrices that
have ppose P equal the identity there
there are more of them than just
permutations but my point right now is
the permutations are like a little group
in the middle in the in the center
of uh these matrice these special
matrices okay so now we know how many
there
are 24 in the case of there are 24 4x4
permutations there are 5 factorial which
is 120 5 * 24 would bump us up to 120 so
listing all the 5 by5 permutations would
be uh not so much fun
okay so that's that's
permutations now also in section 27 is
some discussion of transposes and can I
just complete that
discussion uh first of
all I haven't even transposed a matrix
on the board here have I so I better do
it so suppose I take a matrix like 1 2 4
1 so I it's a rectangular Matrix 3x two
and I want to transpose
it so what's its I'll use I'll use a t
although mat lab would use a
prime and and the result will be I'll
write it here because this was three
rows and two columns this was a 3x2
matrix the transpose will be two rows
and three columns 2
by3 so
it's short and wider and of course that
row that column becomes a
row that column becomes the other row
and at the same time that row became a
column this row became a column oh
what's the general formula for the
transpose so the
transpose I you see you see it in
numbers what I'm going to write is the
same thing in
symbols the numbers are the clearest of
course but in symbols
if I take a
transpose and I ask what number is in
row I and column J of a
transpose well it came out of a it came
out of a by this flip across the main
diagonal and actually it was the number
in
a which was in row J column
I so the row and column IND in the row
and column numbers just get reversed the
row number becomes the column number the
column number becomes the row number no
problem okay now a
special the best
matrices we could say in in a lot of
applications symmetric matrices show up
so can I just call attention to
symmetric
matrices what does that mean what does
that word symmetric mean it means that
this transposing doesn't change the
Matrix a transpose equals
a and an
example so let's take a
matrix that's symmetric so whatever is
sitting on the
diagonal but now what's above the
diagonal like a one had better be
there a seven had better be here a nine
had better be there there's a symmetric
Matrix I I happen to use all positive
numbers as its entries that's not the
point the point is that if I transpose
that Matrix I get it back again so
symmetric matrices have this property a
transpose equals a I guess at this
point I'm just asking you
to notice this family of matrices that
are unchanged by
transposing and they're easy to identify
of
course you know it's not maybe so easy
before we had a case where the transp
gave the
inverse that's highly important but not
so simple to see this is the case where
the transpose gives the same Matrix back
again that's totally simple to
see okay and actually maybe I could even
say when would we get such a
matrix for example this that Matrix is
absolutely far from symmetric right the
transpose isn't even in the same shape
because it's rectangular it turns the it
turns on its lies down on its
side but let me tell you a way to get a
symmetric Matrix out of this multiply
those together if if I multiply this
rectangular so I call it R for
rectangular so that let that be r or
rectangular Matrix and let that be our
transpose which it is then I think that
if I
multiply those together I get a
symmetric Matrix can I just do it with
the
numbers and then ask you why how did how
did I know it would be symmetric so so
I'm so my point is that R transpose R is
always
symmetric
okay and I'm going to do it for that
particular R transpose R which was let's
see the column was 124
331 I called that one R transpose didn't
I and I called this guy one two 4 331 I
called that R should we just do that
multiplication okay so up here I'm
getting a 10 next to it I'm getting two
and N I'm getting an
11 next to that I'm getting four and
three a 7 now what do I get there this
11 came from 13 * 23 right Row one
column two what goes here row two column
one but no difference 13 23 or 23 13
same thing it's going to be an 11 that's
the
Symmetry I can continue to fill it out
what oh let's get that seven that seven
will show up down here too and then four
more numbers that seven will show up
here because 13 * 41 gave the seven but
also 41 * 13 will give that seven do you
see that it
works actually do do you want to do you
want to see it work also in Matrix
language I mean that's quite convincing
right that seven
is no
accident the 11 is no
accident but just tell me how do I know
if I transpose this guy how do I know
it's
symmetric well I'm going to transpose
it and when I transpose
it I'm hoping I get the Matrix back
again so can I transpose R transpose R
so just so why why
well my suggestion is take the
transpose that's the only way to show it
symmetric take the transpose and see
that it didn't change okay so I take the
transpose of R transpose
R how do I do
that this is our little practice on the
rules for
transposes so the rule for transp
oses is the order gets reversed just
like
inverses which we did
prove same rule for
transposes and which we'll now use so
the order gets reversed it's this it's
the transpose of that that comes
first and the transpose of
this that comes now is that yeah that's
what I have to right
right this is a product of two matrices
and I want it transpose so I put the
matrices in the opposite order and I
transpose them but what have I got here
what is our transpose
transpose well don't all speak at
once R transpose transpose I flipped
over the diagonal I flipped over the
diagonal again so I've got
R and then that's just my point that if
I started with this Matrix I transposed
it I got it back
again so that's the
check without using
numbers but with it checked in two lines
that I always get symmetric matrices
this way and actually that's where they
come from in so many practical applic
a
okay so now I've said something today
about
permutations and about
transposes and about
Symmetry and I'm ready for chapter 3 can
we take a
breath the tape won't take a breath but
the lecturer will because to tell you
about Vector space is
is we really have to start now and think
okay listen up what are vector
spaces and what are
subspaces okay
so the point is
the main operations that we do what do
we do with
vectors we add them we know how to add
two
vectors we multiply them by numbers
usually called scalers if we have a
vector we know what 3v is if we have a
vector V and W we know what v+ w is
those are the those are the two
operations that we've got to we've got
to be able to do to legitimately talk
about a space of
vectors the requirement is that we
should be able to add the things and
multiply by numbers and that there
should be some decent rules satisfied
okay so let me start with examples so
I'm talking now about Vector
spaces and I'm going to start with
examples let me say again what this word
space is meaning when I say that word
space that means to me that I've got a
bunch of vectors A Space of
vectors but not just any bunch of
vectors the it has to be a a a space of
vectors has to be has to allow me to do
the operations that vectors are for I
have to be able to add vectors and
multiply by numbers I have to be able to
take linear combinations well where did
we meet linear combinations we met them
back
in say in
R2 so there's there's a vector space
what's that Vector
space so
R2 is telling me I'm talking about real
numbers
and I'm talking about two real numbers
so this is
all twodimensional
vectors
real such
as well I'm not going to be able to list
them all but let me put a few down
0 pi
e so
on and it's
natural
okay let's see I guess I should do
Algebra
first algebra means what can I do to
these vectors I can add them I can add
that to that and how do I do it a
component at a time of course 32 added
to 0 0 gives me uh 32 sorry about that
32 added to Pi e gives me 3 + Pi 2 plus
e oh you know what it does and you know
the picture that goes with it there's
the vector
32 and often the picture has an
arrow the vector 0 0 which is a highly
important Vector it's got like the most
important here is there and of course
it's not much of an arrow
uh Pi E I have to remember Pi is about
three and a little more e is about two
and a little more so maybe there's Pi
E I never drew Pi E
before the it's just natural to this
this is the first
component on the horizontal and this is
the
second component
going up the
vertical okay and the whole plane is
R2 so
R2
is we could say the plane the XY
plane that's what everybody
thinks but the point is
it's a vector space because all those
vectors are in there if I
removed one of them suppose I removed Z
0 suppose I tried to take the considered
the XY plane with a puncture with a
point removed like the origin that' be
like awful to take the origin away why
is
that why do I need the origin there
because I have to be allowed if I had
these other vectors I have to be allowed
to multiply 32 this was
32 by anything by any scalar including
zero I've got to be allowed to multiply
by zero and and and and the results got
to be there I can't do without that
point and I have to be able to add 32 to
the the opposite guy Min -3
-2 and if I add those I'm back to the
origin again no way I can do without the
origin every Vector space has got that
zero Vector in
it okay that's an easy Vector space
because we have a natural picture of it
okay e similarly easy is
R3 this would be all let me go up a
little
here this would
be R3 three would be
all threedimensional vectors or should I
say
vectors
with three real
components okay let me just just to be
sure we're we're together let me take
the vector 320
is that a vector in R2 or
R3 definitely it's an
R3 that it's got three components one of
them happens to be zero but that's
perfectly okay number so that's a vector
in
R3 we don't we we don't want to mix up
the I mean keep these vectors straight
and keep RN straight so what's
rn rn
so this is
our big example is all vectors with n
components and I'm making these darn
things column
vectors can I can I try to follow that
convention that they'll be column
vectors and their components should be
real real
numbers later we'll need complex numbers
and complex vectors but much
later okay so that's a Vector
space now let's see what's what do I
have to tell you about Vector
spaces I said the most important thing
which is that we can
add any two of these and we're still in
R2 we can multiply by any number and
we're still in R2 we can take any
combination and we're still in R2 and
same goes for
RN uh honest
requires me to mention that this these
operations of adding and multiplying
have to
obey a few rules like we can't just
arbitrarily say okay the sum of 32 and
Pi e is 0 0 it's
not the sum of 32 and minus 32 is 0 Z so
oh I'm not going to the the book
actually lists the eight
rules that the addition and and
multiplication have to satisfy but they
do they certainly satisfy it in RN and
and usually it's not those eight rules
that are are in
doubt what's what what the question
is can we do those those additions and
do we stay in the space let me show you
a case where you
can't so suppose this is this is going
to be not not a vector
space suppose I take the XY plane so
that's R2 that is a vector
space now suppose I just take part of
it just this just this one just this is
one
quarter of the vector
space all the vectors with positive
or at least not negative
components can I add
those
safely yes if I add a vector with like
two 32 to another Vector like 56 I'm
still up in this quarter no problem with
adding but there's a heck of a problem
with multiplying by scalers because
there's a lot of scalers that will take
me out of this quarter plane like
negative ones if I took 32 and I
multiplied by
minus5 I'm way down here so that's not a
vector space because it's not closed is
the right word it's not closed under
multiplication by all real
numbers so a vector space has to be
closed under multiplication and addition
of vectors in other words linear
combinations so it
means that if I give you a few vectors
yeah look here's an important here now
we're getting to some really important
Vector spaces well RN like they are the
most
important but we will be interested in
so in Vector spaces that are inside
RN Vector spaces
that follow the
rules but they we don't need all of of
see there we we started with R2
here and took part of it and messed it
up what we got was not a vector space
now tell me a vector space that
is part of
R2 and is still safely we can multi mply
we can add and we stay in the in this
smaller Vector space so it's going to be
called a Subspace so I'm going to change
this bad example to a good
one okay so I'm I'm going to start again
with
R2 but I'm going to take an example that
is a vector space so it'll be a vector
space inside
R2 and we'll call that a
Subspace of
R2 okay what can I do it's got something
in
it suppose it's got this Vector in it
okay if that Vector is in my little
Subspace and it's a true Subspace then
there's got to be some more in it right
I have to be able to multiply that by
two
and that and that double Vector has to
be included have to be able to multiply
by zero that vector or by a half or by
3/4 all these vectors or by minus a half
or by minus
one I have to be able to multiply by any
number so that is going to say that I
have to have that whole
line do you see
that once I get a vector in there I've
got the whole line of all multiples of
that Vector I can't I can't have a
vector space without include without
extending to to get those multiples in
there now I still have to check
addition but that comes out okay this
line is going to work because I could
add something on the line to something
else on the line and I'm still on the
line so so example
so this is all
examples example of a Subspace our
example is a
line in
R2 actually not just any
line if I took this
line would that so all the vectors on
that line so that vector and that vector
and this vector and this vector
so in in
lighter type I'm drawing something that
doesn't work it's not a Subspace the
line in R2 to be a Subspace the line in
R2 must go
through the zero
Vector because why is this line no good
let me do a dashed line
because if I multiply that Vector on the
dashed line by zero then I'm down here
I'm not on the dashed line Zero's got to
be every Subspace has got to contain
zero because I must be allowed to
multiply by zero and that will always
give me the zero
Vector
okay now I was going to make create some
subspaces
oh while I'm in R2
why don't we think of all the
possibilities R2 there can't be that
many so what are the possible subspaces
of R2 let me list them so all sub so so
I'm listing now the
subspaces of
R2 and one possibility that we always
allow is all of R2 the whole thing the
whole
space that counts as a Subspace of
itself you always want to allow that
then the
others are
lines any
line a line meaning infinitely far in
both directions
through the the
zero so that's a that's like the whole
Space that's like whole 2D space this is
like one dimension is is that is this
line the same as R1 no I don't you could
say it looks a lot like R1 R1 was just a
line and this is a line but this is a
line inside R2 this the vectors here
have two components so that's not the
same as R1 because there the vectors
only have one
component very close you could say but
not no not the same okay and now there's
a third
possibility there's a third
Subspace that's of R2 that's not uh not
the whole thing and it's not a
line it's even
less it's just the zero Vector alone the
zero Vector alone only
only I'll often call this Subspace Z
just for zero here's a line L here's a
plane all of our2 so do you see that the
zero Vector is
okay you would just to understand
subspaces we have to know the rules and
knowing the rules means that we have to
see that yes the zero vector by
itself just this guy alone satisfies the
rules why is that oh it's too dumb to
tell
you if I took that and added it to
itself I'm still there if I took that
and multiply by 17 I'm still there so
I've I've done the operations adding and
multiplying by numbers that are required
and I didn't go outside this one point
space so that's always that's the
littlest Subspace the the largest
Subspace is the whole thing and in
between come all whatever is in between
okay so for example what's in between
for R3 so if I'm in ordinary three
dimensions the subspaces are all of R3
at one extreme the zero Vector at at the
bottom uh and
then a plane a plane through the
origin or a line a line through the
origin so with R3
the subspaces were
R3 plain through the origin blind
through the origin and the zero vector
by itself 0 0 0 Z just that single
Vector okay you've got the
idea but the now comes the the the
reality is what are these where do these
subspaces come how do they come out of
matrices and I want to
take this
Matrix oh let me take that Matrix so I
want to create some
subspaces out
of that
Matrix well one
Subspace
is from The
Columns okay
so so this is the important
Subspace the first important Subspace
that comes from that Matrix I'm going
let me call it a again back to
uh okay I'm looking at The Columns of
a those are vectors in
R3 so the columns are in R3 columns are
in
R3 so I want those columns to be in my
Subspace now I can't just put two
columns in my Subspace and call it a
Subspace what do I have to throw in if
I'm going to put those two columns in
what else has got to be there to have a
Subspace I must be able to add those
things so the sum of those columns
so these columns are in
R3
and I have to be able I'm going to I
want that to be in my Subspace I want
that to be in my Subspace but therefore
I have to be able to multiply them by
anything 0 z0 has got to be in my
Subspace I have to be able to add them
so that four five5 is in the Subspace
I've got to be able to add one of these
plus three of these that'll give me some
other
Vector I have to be able to take all the
linear
combinations so so these are columns in
in R3 and all
their linear
combinations
form a
Subspace what do I mean by linear
combinations I mean multiply that by
something multiply that by something and
add the two operations of linear algebra
multiplying by numbers and adding
vectors and if I include all the results
then I'm guaranteed to have a
Subspace I'm I've done I've done my the
job and we'll give it a name the column
space
called the column space
column
space and maybe I'll call it C of a c
for column
space there's an idea there that you
want that this is the like the central
idea for today's
lecture
is got a few
vectors not satisfied with a few vectors
we want a space of vectors the vectors
are in these vectors in are in R3 so our
space of vectors will be vectors in
R3 the key ideas we have to be able to
take their combinations so tell me
geometrically if I drew all these
things like if I drew 124 that would be
somewhere maybe there if I drew 331 who
knows might be I don't know I'll say
there for there's column
one there's column two what else what's
in the whole column
space how do I draw the whole column
space
now I take all combinations of those two
vectors do I get well I guess I actually
listed the possibilities do I get the
whole
space do I get a
plane I get more than a line that's for
sure and I certainly get more than the
zero Vector but I do get the zero Vector
included what do I get if I combine take
all the
combinations of two vectors in
R3 so I'm I've got all this stuff on
that I get that that whole line gets
filled out that whole line gets filled
out but all in between gets filled out
between the two lines because I I
allowed to add something from one line
something from the other
you see what's coming I'm getting a
plane that's my and it's through the
origin those two
vectors namely
124 and
331 when I take all their combinations I
fill out a whole plane please think
about
that that's the picture you have to see
you sure have to see it in R3 because
we're going to do it in
r10 and we may take a combination of
five vectors in r10 and what will we
have uh God knows it's some
Subspace we'll have five vectors they
all have 10 components we take their
combinations we don't have
R5 because our vectors have 10
components
and we possibly have like some
five-dimensional flat thing going
through the origin for
sure well of course if those five
vectors were all on a line then we would
only get that line so you see there like
other possibilities here it depends what
it depends on those five
vectors just like if our two columns had
been on the same line then the column
space would have been only a line here
it was a
plane
okay I'm going to stop at that point
that's the central idea of the the great
example of how to create a Subspace from
a
matrix take its columns take their
combinations all their linear
combinations and you get the column
space
and that's the central sort
of we're we're looking at linear algebra
at a higher level when I look at a I
want to look at ax equal B that'll be
the first thing in the next
lecture how is that how do I understand
ax equal B in this language in this new
language of vector spaces and column
spaces and what are other subspaces so
the column space is a big one
there are others to
come okay thanks